# GOWTHAMI SOMEPALLI

College Park, Maryland, USA

voice: (+1) 475-228-4318 · email: gowthami@umd.edu

web: https://somepago.github.io

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is focused on understanding the failure modes of deep learning models, both discriminative and generative. Lately, my efforts have primarily centered on understanding multimodal generative models, particularly Text-to-Image Diffusion models and Video Language Models.

#### **EDUCATION**

# University of Maryland, College Park

Aug. 2019 - Present

M.S. + Ph.D. in Computer Science (4.0/4.0)Kulkarni fellow, Amazon Internship Fellowship

Advisor: Tom Goldstein

# **Indian Institute of Technology Madras**

Bachelors + Masters in Mechanical Engineering

Advisor: Raghu Prakash

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Visit my Google Scholar T2ezBDsAAAAJ for complete list

• Understanding and Mitigating Copying in Diffusion Models NeurIPS, 2023 G. Somepalli, V. Singla, M. Goldblum, J. Geiping, T. Goldstein

• Baseline defenses for adversarial attacks against aligned language models web, 2023 N. Jain, Y. Wen, G. Somepalli, J. Kirchenbauer, P.Y. Chiang, M. Goldblum, A. Saha, J. Geiping, T. Goldstein

• Diffusion Art or Digital Forgery? Investigating Data Replication in Diffusion Models **CVPR**, 2023 G. Somepalli, V. Singla, M. Goldblum, J. Geiping, T. Goldstein TechCrunch coverage - link

• How much Data is Augmentation Worth? web, ICLR 2023 J. Geiping, G. Somepalli, R. Shwartz-Ziv, A. G. Wilson, T. Goldstein, M. Goldblum

• Investigating Reproducibility and Double Descent from the DB Perspective web, CVPR (Oral) 2022 G. Somepalli, L. Fowl, A. Bansal, P. Yeh-Chiang, Y. Dar, R. Baraniuk, M.GoldBlum, T. Goldstein

 SAINT: Improved NNs for Tabular Data via Row Attention and Contrastive PT web, NeurIPS TRLW 2022 G. Somepalli, M. Goldblum, A. Schwarzschild, C.B. Bruss, T. Goldstein 300+ stars on Github

• PatchGame: Learning to Signal Mid-level Patches in Referential Games web, NeurIPS 2021 K. Gupta, G. Somepalli, Anubhav, V. Jayasundara, M. Zwicker, A. Shrivastava

• Unsupervised Anomaly Detection with Adversarial Mirrored AutoEncoders web, UAI (Oral) 2021 G. Somepalli, Y. Wu, Y. Balaji, B. Vizumuri, S. Feizi

web, PLOS CompBio 2021 • FUGUE: Characterizing functional genes across human tissues G. Somepalli, S. Sahoo, S. Hannenhalli

• Adversarial Training against Poisons and Backdoors (pre-print) J. Geiping, L. Fowl, G. Somepalli, M. Goldblum, M. Moeller, T. Goldstein

## WORK EXPERIENCE

Meta AI 2023 - Present Research Internship New York, NY

• Long video understanding with LLMs.

2022 - 2022Amazon AWS AI

Summer Internship

• Improving the reproducibility and consistency of deep learning models for object detection and classification tasks.

#### University of Maryland and National Cancer Institute

College Park, MD

2019 - 2020

web, 2021

Aug. 2006 - Dec. 2011

Student Researcher

- Worked with Prof. Sridhar Hannenhalli on understanding the tissue-level function of genes, synthetic lethality in the context of selective cancer therapy and cancer development using single-cell data.
- Developed a supervised machine learning model to rank genes in a specific tissue in terms of functionality. The model uses tissue-specific expression-derived and network-derived features.

• Worked on a model to predict trigger mutations in cancer development using single-cell data.

Flipkart 2017 - 2018

Business Manager - Sell side

Bengaluru, India

• Led the demand planning and forecasting for the TV category; revamped the legacy data collection and modeling techniques. Reduced the overstocking of TVs by 15% and reduced the lost potential sales due to out-of-stock issues by 10% within my 6 months of joining.

• Won Annual Business Excellence Award for the most business growth via product innovation.

Poolka Technologies
2015-2017
Cofounder
Bengaluru, India

Poolka provides scalable visual recognition APIs to developers & businesses.

- Built Fairi, a fashion assistant chatbot that provides fashion recommendations based on social media trends and users' existing wardrobe. Iterated & improved the product with 2000+ beta users.
- Selected for Microsoft Bizspark and IBM Global Entrepreneur Program. (>\$20000 cloud credits per year)

#### General Electric, Oil & Gas

2013 - 2015

Engineer/ Synergy Leader

Bengaluru, India

As a technologist in GE, I worked primarily on following two projects -

- Upgrading reciprocating compressors (RC) for Petrochemical plants Led team that designed and validated various RC components. Awarded **Project of the Quarter** (Oct 2014- Dec 2014) and the automation work on Torsional Vibration Analysis won **Kaizen Award** (Mar 2015).
- GE-Cameron Synergy Was single point of contact in Bangalore during the GE acquisition of Cameron. Performed Root Cause Analysis (RCA) for multiple Cameron products. Was accoladed by Senior management GE Oil & Gas, Italy for my role in the synergy.

#### INVITED TALKS

• ICML GenLaw workshop - Understanding Data Replication in Diffusion Models	July 2023
• Google US, ML Collective, TikTok US - Understanding Data Replication in Diffusion Models	s 2023
• WiML workshop @NeurIPS - Investigating Reproducibility from the DB Perspective	Nov 2022
• G-Research, UK - SAINT: Transformers for tabular data.	Nov 2022
• Google Research, India - Can Neural Nets Learn the Same Model Twice?	Apr 2022
• TOPML Workshop - Investigating Double Descent from the DB Perspective.	Mar 2022
• ML Seminar Series, UMD - Transformers for Vision - a mini survey.	Oct 2021
• Headstart, Bengaluru - Learnings from running a B2B tech startup in India.	2017

# SHORT PROJECTS

## Predicting side-effects of drugs and drug combinations

web, Spring 2020

Supervisor: Hector C. Bravo, (Prof. in Department of Computer Science, UMD)

• Built a self-attention based approach to predict Adverse Side Reactions (ADRs). The neural network model exploits know drug protein reactions and protein protein reactions and can be used to predict ADRs in the early stages of drug development. Improved SOTA approaches by 5% AUPRC.

## **SKILLS**

LanguagesPython, C, R, JavaScript, IATEXLibraries/FrameworksPyTorch/Tensorflow, DockerPlatformsMacOS/Linux

#### **MISCELLANEOUS**

• Kulkarni fellowship for summer research (web).

2021

• Reviewer - NeurIPS, ICLR, CVPR

2022-Present

• Founder of @MLSummaries twitter and medium accounts. 4000+ followers.

2021-Present

• Initiated student-led Machine Learning Seminar Series, UMD.

2021-Present

• Mentor: Tech + Research program in Technica.

2020, 2023

• Master's research Scholarship by Ministry of Human Resources and Development, Govt. of India.

May 2010

• National Talent Search Exam Scholarship by Govt. of India.

2005-11

• Prathibha Award by Andhra Pradesh State Govt.

2003